<chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction to &userial;</title>
    <para>
    &userial; is an Open Source USB to &i2c;/&spi;/&gpio; bridge.
    The board uses an &link_atmel; AT90USB647 chip and provides the following interfaces: 
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>1 &times; USB interface (serial emulation, to the PC)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>1 &times; &jtag; port</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>1 &times; &i2c; port</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>1 &times; &spi; port</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>8 &times; General purpose digital I/O (&gpio;) lines</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>4 &times; Analog to Digital (&adc;) converters</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    The board communicates with the host computer using a CDC (USB communications device class).
    This makes it easy to use &userial; without installing a device driver or special libraries.
    Under Windows it is necessary to install a <filename>.inf</filename> file while Linux and Mac OS
    will recognise the device correctly as serial port without particular configuration.
    Due to the ASCII based command interface it is easy to control devices manually with just a terminal emulation.
    This makes it easy to obtain quick results, to configure devices on-the-fly or to control prototyping boards in a straight-forward way.
    </para>

    <para>
    Schematics and firmware are available to the public.
    The firmware is released under the terms of the
    <ulink url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.php">MIT license</ulink>
    and the hardware is released under the terms of the
    <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
    &userial; is based on Dean Camera's &link_lufa; (Lightweight USB Framework for AVRs) library.
    </para>

    <para>
    As of version 1.9, &userial; firmware also supports the &link_bumbleb; board.
    The command structure is the same, but caution must apply due to some hardware differences.
    The main differences are more GPIO ports (ports 'A' through 'D'),
    a missing hardware &i2c; interface (the &i2c; interface is implemented as bit-banging master on port D4/D5),
    and no ADC support.
    </para>

</chapter>
